A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Art Purchase Program FA762
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Art Purchase Program
1966-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ritchie, Andrew Carnduff
Ford Foundation
FA762
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
The Art Purchase Program files were gifted to the Ford Foundation archives by Melinda A. Agsten, Executrix of the Estate of Jane T. Ritchie, Andrew Ritchie's wife, in 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC
Biographical / Historical
In March 1966 the Ford Foundation appointed Andrew Carnduff Ritchie (1907-1978), Director of the Yale University Art Gallery, as a consultant to select and purchase works of art for the Foundation's new headquarters building in New York City. The appointment was to last approximately one year.
Ritchie's career included positions as Director, Albright Art Gallery (now, Albright-Knox Gallery) from 1942-1949; Director of the Painting and Sculpture Department, Museum of Modern Art from 1949-1957, and Director, Yale University Art Gallery from 1957-1971. During World War II Ritchie served with the celebrated "Monuments Men" in the Monuments, Fine Arts, and Archives (MFAA) section of the U.S. Army, as a representative of the Commanding General in Austria.
See also the Andrew Carnduff Ritchie papers in the Archives of American Art: http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/andrew-carnduff-ritchie-papers-8152.
Arrangement
Arranged in 4 series: 1. Administrative files; 2. Index to artists and artworks; 3. Dealer files; 4. Photographs of artworks.
Scope and Contents
Consists of administrative files, dealer files, artist indexes and photos.
Related Materials
Ford Foundation Art Purchase Program files likely maintained by the Ford Foundation's Building Services department can be accessed here: FA1723, Ford Foundation records, Building Services, Ford Foundation artwork photographs
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art collections; Art patronage; Photographs
- Administrative files, 1966-1967; 1; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Art Purchase Program - Correspondence and memos, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1, 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondents include Andrew Ritchie, Verne S. Atwater, and Wilson McNeil Lowry.
  - Ford Foundation Overseas Representatives' suggestions for Art Purchase Program, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3, 4)
    Correspondence between Andrew Ritchie and Ford Foundation Overseas Representatives regarding suggestions for collecting art by artists of the countries/regions covered by the Foundation's grant making programs. Representatives include: Stacey Widdicombe in Brazil, John Nagel in Argentina, Douglas Ensminger in India, Haldore Hanson in Pakistan, Robert Wickham in Mexico, James D. Hardy in Tunisia, David Heaps in Nigeria, Robert Bunnell in the Philippines, Francis X. Sutton in Kenya, and James S. Lipscomb in United Arab Republic (Egypt).
  - Purchase records, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Special Purchase account sheets (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art Purchase - posibilities, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shipping materials, Customs Invoices, and Artist Declaration forms, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 'Expect to Receive' forms (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Framing of artworks, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Art Purchase Program - Second stage, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter of Gift - Estate of Jane T. Ritchie, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Correspondence between Melinda A. Agsten, Executrix of the Estate of Jane T. Ritchie (the wife of Andrew Ritchie) and the Ford Foundation's Archivist, Ann C. Newhall.
- Index to artists and artworks, 2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box; 4x6 inch index cards.
  Index is arranged A-Z by artists name. Each index card includes artist's name, artwork's title, medium, dimensions, invoice status, copy photograph availability, condition, dealer name, and purchase price.
  - Index to artists and artworks: A - J (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Index to artists and artworks: K - R (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Index to artists and artworks: S - Z (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Index to artists and artworks: Dealers - Domestic (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Index to artists and artworks: Dealers - Foreign (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Dealer files, 1966-1968; 3; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Thos. Agnew and Sons, London (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Arcade Gallery, London (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - L' Art Ancien, Zurich, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 18, 19)
  - Asahi Art Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Berggruen and Cie, Paris (Box 2, Folder 21, 22)
  - Alice Boney, Tokyo, Japan (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hector Brame, Paris (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ernest Brown adn Phillips, Ltd., London (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Contemporary Art Establishment, Vaduz, Liechtenstein (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Durlacher Bros., New York (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Philip C. Duschnes, New York (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mrs. Walter Feilchenfeldt, Zurich, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 29, 30)
  - Yvonne French, London (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Robert Frank, London (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sven Gahlin, Ltd., London (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gimpel and Hanover Galerie, Zurich, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hanover Gallery, London (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - K.J. Hewett, London (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Edwin D. Hewitt, Tokyo, Japan (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bernard Houthakker, Amsterdam, The Netherlands (Box 2, Folder 38, 39)
  - John Howell Books, San Francisco (Box 2, Folder 40, 41)
  - Kennedy Galleries, Inc., New York (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - M. Knoedler and Co. Inc., New York (Box 2, Folder 43, 44)
  - Mathias Komor, New York (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - August Laube adn Sohn, Zurich, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 46, 47)
  - R.E. Lewis, Inc., San Francisco (Box 2, Folder 48, 49)
  - David Magee, San Francisco (Box 2, Folder 50, 51)
  - Marlborough-Gerson Gallery, New York (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mayuyama and Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Nystad Antiquairs, The Hague (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Christopher Powney, London (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Dr. Willi Raeber, Basel, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Galerie Rosengart, Lucerne, Switzerland (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Schaeffer Galleries, Inc., New York (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - H.L. Shickman Gallery, New York (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Charles E. Slatkin, Inc. Galleries, New York (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Spink and Son, Ltd., London (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - B. Weinreb, Ltd., London (Box 2, Folder 62, 63)
- Photographs of artworks, 4; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document boxes; Mostly 8x10 inches, black and white.
  Verso of photographs includes artist's name, title, medium, dimensions, and dealer.
  - Photographs of artworks: A - B (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Photographs of artworks: C - D (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Photographs of artworks: E - F (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Photographs of artworks: G - H (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Photographs of artworks: I - J (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Photographs of artworks: K - L (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Photographs of artworks: M - N (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Photographs of artworks: P (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Photographs of artworks: R - S (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Photographs of artworks: T, V, W, Y (Box 3, Folder 73)